<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="safe_numerics.rationale">
  <title>Rationale and FAQ</title>

  <qandaset defaultlabel="number">
    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Is this really necessary? If I'm writing the program with the
        requisite care and competence, problems noted in the introduction will
        never arise. Should they arise, they should be fixed "at the source"
        and not with a "band aid" to cover up bad practice.</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>This surprised me when it was first raised. But some of the
        feedback I've received makes me thing that it's a widely held view.
        The best answer is to consider the cases in the section <link
        linkend="safe_numerics.tutorial">Tutorials and Motivating
        Examples</link>.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Can safe types be used as drop-in replacement for built-in
        types?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>Almost. Replacing all built-in types with their safe
        counterparts should result in a program that will compile and run as
        expected. In some cases compile time errors will occur and adjustments
        to the source code will be required. Typically these will result in
        code which is more correct. See <link
        linkend="safe_numerics.drop_in_replacement">drop-in
        replacement</link>.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Why is Boost.Convert not used?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>I couldn't figure out how to use it from the
        documentation.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Why is the library named "safe ..." rather than something like
        "checked ..." ?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>I used "safe" in large part this is what has been used by other
        similar libraries. Maybe a better word might have been "correct" but
        that would raise similar concerns. I'm not inclined to change this.
        I've tried to make it clear in the documentation what the problem that
        the library addressed is</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Given that the library is called "numerics" why is floating
        point arithmetic not addressed?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>Actually, I believe that this can/should be applied to any type
        T which satisfies the type requirement "Numeric" type as defined in
        the documentation. So there should be specializations
        safe&lt;float&gt; et. al. and eventually safe&lt;fixed_decimal&gt;
        etc. But the current version of the library only addresses integer
        types. Hopefully the library will evolve to match the promise implied
        by it's name.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Isn't putting a defensive check just before any potential
        undefined behavior is often considered a bad practice?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>By whom? Is leaving code which can produce incorrect results
        better? Note that the documentation contains references to various
        sources which recommend exactly this approach to mitigate the problems
        created by this C/C++ behavior. See <link
        linkend="seacord1"><citation>Seacord</citation></link>, <ulink
        url="https://www.cert.org">Software Engineering Institute - Carnegie
        Mellon University</ulink></para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>It looks like the implementation presumes two's complement
        arithmetic at the hardware level. So this library is not portable -
        correct? What about other hardware architectures?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>As far as is known as of this writing, the library does not
        presume that the underlying hardware is two's compliment. However,
        this has yet to be verified in a rigorous way.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Why do you specialize numeric_limits for "safe" types? Do you
        need it?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>safe&lt;T&gt; behaves like a "number" just as int does. It has
        max, min, etc Any code which uses numeric limits to test a type T
        should works with safe&lt;T&gt;. safe&lt;T&gt; is a drop-in
        replacement for T so it has to implement all the operations.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>According to C/C++ standards, unsigned integers cannot overflow
        - they are modular integers which "warp around". Yet the safe numerics
        library detects and traps this behavior as errors. Why is that?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>The guiding purpose of the library is to trap incorrect
        arithmetic behavior - not just undefined behavior. Although a savvy
        user may understand and keep present in his mind that an unsigned
        integer is really modular type, the plain reading of an arithmetic
        expression conveys the idea that all operands are plain integers. Also
        in many cases, unsigned integers are used in cases where modular
        arithmetic is not intended, such as array indexes. Finally, the
        modulus for such an integer would vary depending upon the machine
        architecture. For these reasons, in the context of this library, an
        unsigned integer is considered to a representation of a subset of
        integers which is expected to provide correct integer results. Note
        that this decision is consistent with INT30-C, “Ensure that unsigned
        integer operations do not wrap” in the CERT C Secure Coding Standard
        [Seacord 2008]..</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</section>
