<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Case Study: Safety Critical Embedded Controller</title>

  <para>Suppose we are given the task of creating stepper motor driver
  software to drive a robotic hand to be used in micro surgery. The processor
  that has been selected by the engineers is the PIC18F252 manufactured by
  Microchip Corporation. On a processor this small, it's common to use a
  mixture of 8, 16, and 32 bit data types in order to conserve memory space
  and minimize memory footprint and runtime penalty.</para>

  <para>Requirements:<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Algorithm must be verifiable.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Code must match the algorithm.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>No user interface available.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>No user input available.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>No exceptional conditions such as interrupts permitted.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The system has no i/o other than a few pins to control the
        stepper motor.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>Actually this is a pretty common scenario. The only difference in this
  case are the extreme consequences associated with violations of the above
  requirements. We will start making a basic working prototype. This we will
  enhance in a stepwise fashion until all the above requirements are
  met.</para>

  <section>
    <title>First Prototype</title>

    <para>The engineers are still debugging the prototype boards and hope to
    have them ready before the product actually ships. But this doesn't have
    to keep us from working on our code. Searching around the net, we find a
    popular <ulink
    url="../../examples/Generate%20stepper-motor%20speed%20profiles%20in%20real%20time%20%7C%20Embedded.pdf">article</ulink>
    on the operation of stepper motors using simple micro controllers. The
    algorithm is very well explains and it includes a complete <ulink
    url="../../examples/motor.c">code example we can test</ulink>. Starting
    with the original code we make the following changes:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>We create a new file "</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para/>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>
</section>
